Eugene Leontev

Senior Ruby Developer

+995 555 43 35 90 | potehin@gmail.com | linkedin.com/in/madmatvey | github.com/madmatvey

Address: 0179 Georgia, Tbilisi, Irakli Abashidze street 38

SUMMARY

I have over 8 years of experience as a self-employed engineering manager and programmer, specializing in Ruby and JavaScript, in developing highly loaded mobile (iOS/Android) and web applications. I take pride in owning the results of my product team. As an ENTP, I thrive in debates and love tackling challenges. The most satisfaction I get from my engineering work is measuring user satisfaction, completing product iterations based on insights gained from the data.

In my work, I focus on solving real problems and delivering measurable value to users. I work independently to prioritize clean code, solid architecture, and clear communication skills to drive project success. I believe in simplicity and iterative development for building complex systems. I appreciate clear and transparent communication, which is key to project success. I also have experience with analytics platforms (Amplitude) and CRM-systems.

I'm looking for a long-term partnership with a company that values transparency and puts people first, including engineers, customers, and users.

SKILLS

Backend development

Ruby on Rails, Sinatra, API, security, BDD, TDD, RSpec, MVC, scalability, Performance, Functionality Implementation

• Team Leadership

Communication skills, Hiring, Motivation, Decision-making,
Problem-solving, Conflict Resolution, Empathy,
Compassion, Adaptability, Delegation, Mentoring, Distributed Team
• Infrastructure and CI/CD

Docker, K8s, Linux/unix, GitLab, GitHub actions, AWS, S3, Google Cloud Platform

Software development

Ruby, JavaScript, Service Oriented Architectures, Testing and debugging, Git Version Control, Scripting skills, SQL, iOS, Android

• Database and Queues Management

PostgreSQL, MySQL, Redis, Sidekiq, Elasticsearch

Product Thinking

Accountability, Business Requirements, Agile, Technical Design, Iterative development, Prototyping, Data Analysis, Customer-Oriented

COMPETENCIES

Technical Expertise

- Designed and implemented a scalable architecture for a high-load mobile application, resulting in a 92% performance improvement and enhancing its repair capabilities
- Led a team in refactoring a legacy codebase, resulting in a 61% reduction in bugs and significantly enhancing maintainability.
- Implemented procedures for automated server capacity deployment during high-load periods, resulting in a 30-40% streamlining of deployment processes, a 20% reduction in capacity rental costs, and improved system design.
- Implemented and advocated for integrating a test coverage check step into the code review process for proposed changes, resulting in a notable increase in test coverage from 56% to 93% within six months. All significant use cases were successfully covered by tests.

Team Leadership

- Managed a team of 12 developers, cultivating a collaborative environment that resulted in the team consistently meeting project goals ahead of schedule, without experiencing burnout or overwork.
- Provided mentorship to junior developers, enhancing their coding practices and supporting their professional development.
- Facilitated clear communication between team members and stakeholders, ensuring alignment of project goals and priorities.
- Participated in the hiring, interviewing, and onboarding of new team members, with experience in the termination process.
- Implemented MBTI-based personality compatibility and US Army SEAL team-building in recruitment, leading to more productive, autonomous teams.

• Implemented a sprint challenge rule of 80% for new tasks and 20% for technical debt restructuring, ensuring balanced progress in product development.

Problem-Solving

- Identified and resolved a critical performance bottleneck, improving application API response time by 90%.
- Developed a solution for integrating third-party APIs, increasing the application's functionality and usability.
- Resolved a complex technical issue that had stumped previous teams, demonstrating a strong ability to troubleshoot and find innovative solutions.
- As a team leader, developed and implemented a system of 5 key metrics for a high-traffic application, which is now used daily. This
 system enables us to measure Daily Active Users (DAU), Weekly Active Users (WAU), and Monthly Active Users (MAU), monitor
 the uniformity of content distribution, and assess the quality of user behaviour within the application.

EXPERIENCE

01/2023 - 03/2024 San Francisco, USA full-remote

Wallarm (API Security) Lead Ruby Developer

05/2022 - 12/2022 Riga, Latvia full-remote

Eleving Group (fintech auto loans, debts management) Lead Ruby Developer

08/2018 - 04/2022 Samara, Russia hybrid-remote

Appbooster (hi-load mobile application) Team Lead / Senior Ruby Developer

01/2017 - 07/2018 Valencia, Spain full-remote

Bitupper (Cryptocurrency blockchain explorer) CTO / Ruby Developer

EDUCATION

2024 Coursera & GitLab, How to manage a remote team

2021 Harvard College, Cambridge, MA USA, CS50

Higher Education

2005-2007 Urals State University, Yekaterinburg, Computer science in economics

2001-2004 Novosibirsk State Technical University, Novosibirsk, Computing machines, complexes, systems and networks

Languages:

- English B2+ (fluent)
- Russian (native)

Visa status:

I have a work permit as an individual entrepreneur in Georgia. I can work flexibly on a B2B basis. I am considering relocation to Argentina as my next base camp

Hobbies

- Albert Einstein had a hobby of driving a sailboat. It <u>helped him to understand how the universe works</u>. I have a license to captain a sailboat for recreational purposes.
- Playing guitar can stimulate creativity and provide a relaxing break from work.